Okay.
And we've been going through
It started as a medicine Buddha program
and then we started to do
Arya Nagarjuna's
book called Wisdom.
So I'll share a little bit about
something.
And
new text on wisdom. Sometimes it has the
nickname $100.
Huh?
Wait. You have to raise your hand and
get the microphone.
I'm not giving any money just to people
yelling in the class.
No?
Did the mayor have an opinion? I don't
know.
No.
Sure?
Quick. Today. No, cancel that. Too slow.
Uh it's called the Middle Way.
His book is also called the Middle Way.
The name
Middle Way they kind of started with
this book.
And then somebody else wrote a book
called
Entering the Middle Way and that's
Master Chandrakirti.
So Nagarjuna lived around Arya Nagarjuna
lived around 200 AD, almost 2,000 years
ago, almost the time of Christ.
And then 400 years after him, roughly,
came Master Chandrakirti.
We're studying
wisdom.
And we've had six sessions.
And we are going to finish in this
session.
Okay.
Yeah.
And uh
So in in Kyoto we're going to finish 14
years
of learning and here we're finishing. I
don't know if it's 6 years or 6
sessions. It's many ways.
It's probably around 5 years or
something.
And uh
there's um
four chapters left that we have to
finish, okay?
He wrote his book in 27 chapters.
And each chapter is called a pariksha,
which means
an examination here. Not the
Princeton kind of examination.
The checking about something, okay?
And
so we're going to cover the last four
chapters, 24, 25, 26, and 27.
24 is called
an investigation of the Arya truth,
the four higher truths,
truth of suffering, truth of
source of suffering, truth of the
end of suffering, and the truth of the
path to the end, okay?
And he's going to investigate those
four.
That's a pretty long chapter. Uh
40 verses, okay?
And And I started it last time and I
want to do it over.
I want to start over again. So we're
going to do the whole chapter, okay?
Uh
cuz I
I think we can
do more of it. Okay, chapter 25 is
called an investigation of Nirvana,
okay?
And that would be interesting to hear
from the greatest Buddhist master
after Lord Buddha. He's called the
second Buddha sometimes.
Okay?
And there hasn't been anybody since him
except for just a couple
of the same level.
Uh chapter 26,
an investigation of the mayor of
Winrock's
12 links,
okay? The 12 links of dependence, okay?
That's chapter 26.
By the way, at some somewhere all the
mixed nuts books
interact.
intersect.
And chapter seven 27 is called an
investigation of how we view reality.
How do we look at reality?
And that's chapter 27. So, we're going
to cover all
four
chapters.
And
then
each day
I will do some Q&A also.
Is the second class how long, Tim?
75.
So, we'll do some Q&A.
Uh
so,
and my Q&A's are free for all. Free for
all means a
a fight with no rules.
So, if you uh
you know, you can ask any question. I
don't care. Okay? It can be
whatever comes in your heart, you're
welcome to ask. Okay?
Uh
and then we're going to talk more about
the five houses.
Um I see I thought to I have some
I have a presentation about the five
houses each day.
A little more detail about the five
houses
and uh
I thought to do it at the end of this
class instead of the beginning of this
class
because
if you think Sedona people are up right
now
watching this class
I don't think so.
Okay. But, maybe they'll watch it by
maybe they wake up by the end, I'm
thinking.
Okay. So,
I don't know if there's anybody left in
Sedona.
Okay.
All right, let's see here.
Uh
are you guys ready? There should be a
picture of a sunset and a sailboat, I
think.
Tada.
This was uh taken out of my hotel window
last week.
Uh,
what gives the sunset
to the west of Manhattan that
distinctive glow?
It's
it's the uh gasoline factories for the
whole country are right there.
Uh,
it's called Cancer Alley.
Uh, I and I used to go through it twice
a day for for 19 years.
And uh on the bus. So, I was 4 hours on
the
We went down Cancer Alley.
But it gives a wonderful sunset.
Uh,
and then uh you see, what is that?
Hudson River, I think.
And then uh
the the Statue of Liberty is to the
left, but couldn't quite see it.
And there's this beautiful sailboat in
the
You know, here's all these
skyscrapers
and 5 million people coming and going,
and then
there's some
soul out on a sailboat
just enjoying the day, you know,
and I thought it was a beautiful
picture.
To me, it represents uh
Ayn Rand and objectivism, okay?
The sailboat represents uh Ayn Rand and
objectivism because he he's uh
unusual. He he's very very unusual, and
he
only wrote
uh
short
poetic pieces. He didn't write long
philosophy. Oops.
He
poems poems.
But they're like you know, they're
pretty good. They're
He expressed the deepest truth of
emptiness
uh through poetry.
And uh
after him uh about uh 4 500 years later
came uh Master Chandrakirti.
And he wrote a book called
uh Entering the Middle Way,
Madhyamakavatara
So,
getting into the
Middle Way.
And then the Middle Way means Nagarjuna.
Okay?
Nagarjuna lived 700 years after Buddha.
There was a mafia that took over after
Buddha.
It lasted for 600 years.
It was called Stanley
Abhidharma.
And they were nice guys, but uh
dull.
Very dull and long. I It was the first
subject I studied with my teacher for 12
years, 12 long years.
And it was so dry.
And they kind of took over Buddhism
after Lord Buddha. And they made it very
uh mechanical and many lists of things
and
it's it's informative.
But it's dry, you know.
You got to be a
You got to be tough to get through it.
And they didn't talk a lot about
emptiness. They have a short
presentation of emptiness, which is
really interesting. Which we've never
talked about.
Which we could talk about someday.
Uh if you're in the mood. Uh
and then came Aryadeva.
And he also introduced uh
the teachings of Bodhicitta. Okay? So,
he introduced the Bodhisattva uh
ideal
in Buddhism
heavily. The Abhidharma mentions
Buddhism
like one sentence or something. But
then, for Aryadeva, it was his it was
his passion.
So, he's the greatest teacher ever
of emptiness.
And he's the greatest teacher of the
Bodhisattva path.
And actually, when we take Bodhisattva
vows here,
uh we use his ceremony. We use the
ceremony that he wrote,
which still exists. And we we recovered
it. John Braney's project recovered it.
And we translated it and we use it and
it's
it's very, very beautiful. He also uh
was
a He was simple. He He taught everything
simply, but very, very deeply. And also,
he had this uh
traditional connection with the
with the kings of India.
And this was the ancient
model of government. You had a a yogi,
or you had a great emptiness
philosopher,
would be the advisor to the king.
And we have uh that We have several
uh books. Like, one is called Milinda
Pañha in Pali,
uh which in
Sanskrit is Milindapañha, which means
the questions of King Milinda Milin-
Milinda.
And he was a Greek king who uh
reigned in India for a long time.
Alexander attacked India 2,300 years
ago.
And uh took over India. And then he gave
the country to three or four generals
and then he went home, but he died on
the way. He died in Baghdad.
So, um
there were these kings
who were used to
listening to philosophers. I mean, if
you can imagine
the next president of the United States,
she's listening to
Tim.
She's listening to Tim, you know, or
something like that. I mean, that would
be the similar
thing, you know.
And um
I'm just joking, okay? I'm I don't do
politics
in public. Um
So, uh
So, anyway, um
imagine if if the king or queen of the
country
um were And then so, we have some
beautiful books
by Nagarjuna written for kings. A king
called Udayibhadra.
And um
Nick is translating one of those. Uh I
have a beautiful commentary, too. So,
it The reason I wanted to show this
picture was
uh the difference between the two great
emptiness teachers in history.
Okay? And that's Arya Nagarjuna.
Sometimes he's just called the Arya.
And uh
And generally, you get an Arya about
every 500 years or something.
And he he's the
he's the big one after Lord Buddha,
okay?
That would be
that would be 700 years, 6 to 700 years
after Buddha, okay?
And he's so famous as a emptiness master
that we call him sometimes the Arya,
Uh in in the tradition,
it's considered impolite to call him
Nagarjuna. It's like saying, "Hey,
Shin."
"Chen."
Like that. It's just disrespectful, kind
of. Okay? Just so you know, if you're
cool, you say, "Arya Nagarjuna." Okay?
And that's his
real name. Okay?
Uh and I won't go into why he's called
Nagarjuna.
That's a long story.
Uh
if you're interested, uh I put uh
So, Nick uh finished a translation of
Nagarjuna Arya Nagarjuna
earlier called the 60 Verses.
And uh that is done. It went to
publishing.
Our publishing process is a little bit
like
the highways into Manhattan.
So, there's too many books trying to get
out of New Jersey.
Uh
and uh we have a tie-up. We usually have
a congestion.
We have a problem of
too many books and not enough editors.
So,
anyway, his book is done. There's a
beautiful
biography of Arya Nagarjuna in it. Okay?
So, and which was written by my teacher.
And it's quite it's quite good. It's
hard to find a good biography.
The reason I wanted to put this picture
was uh I'm working on a
a book about Chandrakirti. And it was
written by Tsongkhapa.
So, I would say those are the three
greatest emptiness teachers since Lord
Buddha. Okay? And there's nobody close
to them.
I mean, frankly, there's nobody at their
level. There's three. It's Nagarjuna,
Chandrakirti, and and Tsongkhapa.
And
uh so, Tsongkhapa wrote an explanation
of Master Chandrakirti's explanation of
Nagarjuna Arya am
And
uh that was called uh the illumination
of the truth of it.
And it's very very difficult and it's
very very deep and it's very very
complete.
And so I started it 12 years ago when
Veronica's mom was ill.
Uh
I used to hang out in the coffee shop.
Uh we used to go down and Veronica would
take care of her.
And then I would sit in the coffee shop
and
work on this book 12 years ago and uh
So I'm I'm 1,300 pages
finished.
And uh it will be about uh 1,600 pages.
So we're almost finished.
Uh
And uh
just the chapter on emptiness
by the chapter on wisdom
by Master Chandrakirti who follows the
six perfections
in his book roughly. Uh
that
that chapter
is 300 verses, okay?
A typical uh
chapter of Nagarjuna is 20.
Okay?
So think 10 times longer, 15 times
longer. Nagarjuna was a master
of saying things deeply and briefly and
mysteriously.
And then Chandrakirti was more of a
nerd.
And he
explained Nagarjuna but it took 10 times
more pages.
Uh
so we're translating both
uh
in in this book. And then you have Geshe
Kelsang
explanation which is the best in
history.
And I'm not being uh what do you call
it? Prejudiced just cuz I grew up in
that tradition. You
We have
We're we are the only people saving
those books in the world.
And I've been working on them for 50
years and
And so Kapa's unbelievable.
And wonderful.
So it's something we want to save before
we go to another world. Okay? And
we're working on that. So I see it as a
difference between
Nagarjuna's kind of like the sailboat.
And Candrakirti is like all the big
buildings in Manhattan.
You know, like Candrakirti is complex.
And Nagarjuna is simple. And I've been
reading the Sanskrit lately because
it's so old, it's 2,000 years old.
There's a lot of things that are not
clear.
The Sanskrit is
difficult, okay?
I like to show off something I memorized
in 12th
11th grade.
When I was a kid, when I met her.
Uh one block of pearl with a short of
salt and a dog from here said pierce
into the rotten body of every being and
wishing
we should be doing ganders to the floor.
What language?
It's English, okay? It's English 500
years ago, Chaucer.
Chaucer and early Shakespeare, okay?
Uh
So imagine what happened to Sanskrit in
in four or five times that that length
of time.
In 25 centuries, not not five or four
centuries, okay?
So it's difficult. It's really
difficult. And what I wanted to say is
uh
what I've been learning
is that Nagarjuna's Sanskrit is elegant
and beautiful
and short.
And if you're interested in Sanskrit,
that's where you should start.
And then Chandrakirti is complicated.
And and much more much much longer, much
much more complex.
It's beautiful in its own way.
Um but if you're interested to learn
Sanskrit,
I would encourage you to learn
wisdom. The book is called wisdom.
And his style
was short and sweet. Um
and people since him have renamed his
book. He called his book
wisdom.
And then, you know, root text on the
middle way called wisdom. You know,
people made it longer and longer.
But his style, Nagarjuna's style,
is
so beautiful, short and sweet, you know.
So,
if you ever have a chance but that also
makes it
difficult to understand.
Okay? Cuz he doesn't explain things. He
just hits you with a mystery.
He loves riddles.
And you can sit with one of his verses
for a long time.
And so, I'm going to you know, I I
wanted to
share some verses with you.
Uh if you're in a retreat,
there's nothing more delicious
than to take a verse of Nagarjuna and
and sit with it for a day or two days,
okay? They're short
and they're very very deep, okay? And
you go you can go deeper and deeper and
deeper, okay? So, I'm going to give you
some verses.
Uh you could even just
take a photo when they come up, okay?
And by the way, to me,
uh the difference between these three
great masters of emptiness.
Arya Nagarjuna, Master Chandrakirti, and
Jetsun Kunga.
You don't have to call Jetsun Kunga
master cuz Jay means master.
So, um
the difference between them to me
is kind of the difference between the
five houses of ACI.
You know, yeah, I think you can find in
these three ancient masters
you can find a parallel to the five
houses of ACI. And we're going to talk
more about the five houses at the end of
class, okay?
Um
but to me
uh their style represents three
different houses, okay?
And
that's something we're going to talk
about.
Because the point of the houses, partly,
is that we are there's a different house
for everybody.
You see? Like if you're into meditation,
then go to
which house?
Samadhi house. If you're into the
classics, go to classics house.
Guess what I'm into.
Classics house.
Uh
or you can go to What's the last one?
Diamond house. Yeah. So,
we're going to talk about the houses as
we go, okay?
And we're going to start with
we're going to start now. Listen, look
at this.
Not that one.
Yeah, hang on.
Okay. Uh
yeah.
You can take a picture if you want, and
you can meditate on it, okay?
And this
this first verse
of this famous chapter
is interesting.
And it says a lot about Arya Nagarjuna
because
uh
Who wrote the first verse? If you read
it, who wrote it?
I'll I'll read it for you, okay?
If all things are empty, if all these
things are empty,
then nothing can start and nothing can
stop.
According to you, then,
the four higher truths, which is the
basis of all Buddhism,
it's the first teaching Lord Buddha ever
gave,
uh
could not exist at all.
Who's talking?
Yeah, it's Kaccayana. It's uh Who's
there, Kaccayana?
Refreshing. Oh, never mind. It's just
the news guy. Uh
Yeah.
Arya Nagarjuna is starting off one of
the most famous chapters of the most
famous book on emptiness in Buddhism
by allowing someone else to criticize
him.
Okay? And that says something about
Nagarjuna.
You see? He's welcoming.
And then the keyword, you Americans, is
civil debate.
Debate. Civil means polite
debate.
Okay? He's encouraging
polite debate, okay? And he's he's
saying
uh
He's like this, "Oh, did you have
something to say? Please talk first."
Something my wife is always encouraging
me to learn.
Uh
you know, did did you have something to
say?
You know, uh did you want to say
something? And it's so Bodhisattva
to start out his chapter like that. And
it's so
selfless. You see what I mean? He's
thinking of the other person.
He doesn't say, "Let me teach you about
emptiness. I know everything." He does.
But he starts out and he says,
"You have any problem with emptiness?"
And the guy says, "Yeah."
"If everything's empty, nothing works.
Okay? If everything is empty, then
nothing works."
And as a
ACI master,
this is maybe
half the classes you're ever going to
teach
is people who misunderstood emptiness.
Okay?
Misunderstanding emptiness
is a worldwide specialty.
And it's all over the world and
all over history,
you know, the last 2,000 years.
Then you get people sitting and staring
at the wall and trying to see nothing,
you know.
And hitting someone hits them on the
back with a stick if they move.
That And it's such a
BS.
You know, somebody sitting staring at a
wall trying to think about nothing is so
wrong.
100% wrong. Foolish.
You know, it's so anti-Lam Rim. Why?
If you're going to die,
the last thing you want to do is sit and
stare at a wall.
You don't have time.
You know, you don't have time to figure
out life. You know, you got to
think. You got to think about it. You
got to understand. You have to love
other people. You can't sit in your
house and stare at a wall.
You know, so anyway,
very, very famous opening line. Okay?
"Hey, Nagarjuna. Are you Nagarjuna?"
He'll call him Nagarjuna, right? "Hey,
Nagarjuna, you know, if everything's
empty, then nothing works. And then, the
first teaching of the Buddha is
canceled."
Okay? The four truths is canceled.
Doesn't make any sense. If everything
doesn't matter,
if if everything's empty, if there's no
point of anything,
then
why why did Buddha bother to teach these
four truths, you know? Why? Okay? That's
the very famous
beginning. But, I think uh
when you're meditating on it,
maybe it's more important to meditate on
the fact
that he put this verse first
than the emptiness. You see what I mean?
He allows his opponent
to speak first.
And he he honors his opponent, and he's
polite to his opponent, and he clearly
states his opponent's
position. He doesn't try to twist
the opponent. There was a politician on
on the TV yesterday,
and the the interviewer asked this
politician five times in a row the same
question.
And the politician avoided it five
times.
Shamelessly. Like,
you know, just
they said, you know, "What color is the
sky?" And he's like, "I like fish."
You know? And
everyone's like, "Huh?"
And then she said, "No, but what color
is the sky?" And he says, "Also pita."
You know? And then she's And she asked
him five times. And then she's like,
"Okay,
I get it, you know." But, this is
So, what I'm saying is the way he starts
this chapter,
maybe it's more important
that he was
polite
to someone who's attacking his ideas.
And he
he almost seems to
love the other person.
Okay? And maybe that's the message of
the chapter. Okay, I'm just proposing
it.
All right, next
next picture you guys. I got to dig
through them because I got so many.
Yeah.
Uh
So, I'm sorry my my photo agency sold
out to this guy called AI.
And the guys are handsome, so I thought
the ladies would like the four guys. But
uh
but they never quite get the fingers
right.
I don't know what that is, you know.
I want to give them a finger.
But uh never mind.
Um
So,
to me uh these four guys represent the
four truths. Okay?
The four truths. And we'll Who wants to
say them again? Uh
suffering
cause of suffering
end of suffering
how to get to the end.
Uh if you put them in order of
time
if you put them in the order that they
occur
in re- in real life, the order is
different. What would the order be?
The cause of suffering, like you you are
impolite to another debater.
Number two
you suffer. Number three
you practice a path to get out of the
suffering. And number four, you you get
a So, there's two ways to order the four
truths. By the way, noble truth is a bad
bad bad bad translation.
Of uh by some British guy in 1860 and I
don't know, the bad translation survived
and the good translations fade away.
But, it has nothing to do with this
topic, okay? It's a bad translation of
the word
arya, okay? These four principles are
called the arya principles because when
you see emptiness directly, you will
understand these four directly for the
first time, okay?
All right.
There's a traditional uh
relationship
between us and the four truths, okay?
There's a traditional relationship. So,
whenever someone traditionally when they
teach the four truths
they tell you four ways of relating to
the four truths, okay?
And that's a very important principle in
the teaching of Lord Buddha. That was
his first
teaching.
How long between when he got enlightened
and when he taught?
Did he teach the next morning?
He waited seven seven weeks, I think, 49
days.
Uh Stanley Nelson went with me. Well,
they I went to Varanasi
to uh the Sanskrit University and then
they went to Deer Park
which is where Lord Buddha gave gave
this teaching,
uh I think. And then uh yeah, and then
uh
I remember we we got out of the airport
and our taxi was followed by an
elephant.
Uh
for like a couple miles and uh they were
like, "Is that normal, Geshe la?"
And I was like, "Everything It's India,
everything is normal."
So, anyway, uh there's four
uh
just four four things you have to do
if the four truths are correct, okay?
And here they are. Number one,
we call Shepa John. Shepa John means
That's how you should relate to the
first truth. What's the first truth?
Pain, pain.
Suffering, okay? Everything about your
life is pain.
And then
you should And excuse my language, but
you should realize what the hell's going
on.
Okay?
Many people go through the whole life,
get older, die,
and they never figure out what the
hell's going on.
And And And Buddhists like, "Wake up.
You Didn't you notice your grandparents
die? Didn't you notice your parents die?
Didn't you notice On the way here from
Tucson, somebody died?
We We passed them. We weren't them. We
got here.
You know, dying It happens, and we do it
all the time. What's Are you blind? Are
you stupid? Are you crazy? You know?
You going to be on this Someday people
will be, "Oh, look. Look what happened."
I And
it's just foolish to not understand
what's going on. So, the first The
relationship to the first arya truth is,
wake the hell up.
Wake up, you know? Try to see what's
going on.
No one's ever survived this life.
Except a few
Buddhists, maybe. So,
All right? So, first thing, Shepa John
means
you know, wake up. Wake up.
That was how we're supposed to relate to
the first arya truth, okay?
What's your guess? You have to raise
your hand, and I'm not offering a single
dollar.
What's your guess to how we should
relate to the second arya truth?
The second Arya Truth by the way was
where is this stuff coming from?
Microphone.
And
it's too long. It'll take too long.
It's figured out. Figured out. Okay.
Number one,
you know, realize what's happening.
Number two,
figure out where it's coming from.
The classic example is your your
your kitchen sink is leaking. There's
water all over the kitchen floor.
Okay. You can keep mopping it up day
after day after day or you can fix it.
Crawl under the
sink. What did I tell you was important
if you crawl under the sink?
Always wear nice underwear.
And I never know a plumber who listened
to this advice.
They're always showing you anyway.
You know, go look for where is this
stuff coming from? Where is the problem
coming from? Go be curious.
Go look under the sink. Okay. So, the
second action to be taken is
look under the sink, stupid. You know,
don't keep suffering over and over.
Okay. Third, what's our relationship to
the third Arya Truth?
Which is the cessation, stopping.
Stopping the water or stopping the pain.
Get it done.
Get it done. They say achieve. Do it.
Do it. Nike.
Just do it.
Okay. Do it.
Get it done. Stop the pain. It is
possible. It's It's not easy, but it's
possible.
If you work hard, you can do it.
But it
And then that's why we're here. Okay.
Number four,
path path.
Uh we would say follow it.
Okay. So, there's four I would say
there's
Let's make it simple. Four single words.
Pain,
source,
stopping,
path.
And the four actions are realize,
discover,
achieve,
follow. Okay? Four actions.
Okay.
And by the way,
what's hap- happening in Aryadeva's book
at this point is that the other guy is
saying,
"I don't see how you can do it.
I don't see how you can do those four
actions because according to you,
everything's empty.
How can you realize nothing? How can you
discover
nothing? How can you achieve
nothing? How can you follow
nothing?" So, first he says,
the earlier verses in this chapter,
which is called an examination of the
Arya truth. So, first the other guy
comes and he says,
"Look, if everything's empty, there's no
four truths." And Nagarjuna's like, he
plays along. He says, "Why do you say
that?"
And the guy says, "Well, if there is a
four truths,
what are you going to do with them? Are
you going to realize, discover, achieve,
follow?
Cuz they don't exist cuz they're empty.
You're going to realize nothing. You're
going to discover nothing. You're going
to achieve and nothing. You're going to
follow nothing. You're so cool,
Nagarjuna.
You know,
right? I'm starting to feel like that
preacher on my wife's
Uh
we we listen to this cool preacher
sometimes on the on the
radio. Okay.
Okay. So, uh he's still criticizing
Aryadeva. Aryadeva doesn't What do you
call it? He's not a token objector. He
gets his space. Aryadeva, as we would
expect of a Bodhisattva, he gives him
time to make his
objections. He doesn't rush him. He
says, "You got any other critic?" We
never do that, right? Someone criticizes
us and we say, "Oh, that's wonderful.
You have more?
You You want to criticize me more?" You
know, we try to change the subject.
And the guy says like, "Oh, really?
Okay. Yeah, yeah, I can uh see your
point."
Okay.
All right.
Okay, next picture, you guys.
I call it happy in the stream. Okay,
happy in the stream. For once, the AI
got it right.
I think she even has fingers.
Uh some fingers.
And uh
Okay.
What do you think it represents,
American guess? I mean,
Huh?
Yeah, you can say entering the stream.
Right? Gaining stream, we call gaining
stream. Okay, say gaining stream.
Entering the stream.
Uh
if you see
emptiness directly,
then
uh you enter the stream, okay?
And that is a synonym.
Uh you can say the person is an Arya.
Or you can say they are a stream
enterer. $100.
Who's paying all this money?
What?
Uh
when I teach for the university, I bring
up the money
cuz they pay.
But, in the moment, I'd pay. Uh
I forgot what I was going to ask. Um
What?
Haha,
I was kidding, wrong.
Uh
why is it called entering the stream?
Why is it called entering the stream
when you see emptiness directly for the
first time?
And you give the microphone to
There's a corruption
that goes on. The microphone giver
splits the money with the
No, anyway, good.
I'm not sure, but I think the stream of
all the areas before Yeah.
Anybody else?
Because there's no way back.
Good. Nice. $100.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's like um
we went in Manhattan through the Holland
Tunnel.
Like, once you get to the entrance of
the Holland Tunnel, you can't turn
around.
Okay? I mean, people have tried.
Uh people from New Jersey have tried.
But, uh
you would just die.
Okay?
Uh you can't go back, okay? It's a flow.
You will
inevitably, and soon, which means less
than 490 years,
you will achieve
uh nirvana and buddhahood, okay? You're
on your way out. And nothing can stop
you.
And And you couldn't stop it if you
wanted to stop it. Okay, that's cool.
That's called stream entry.
And there are four
there are four such
levels. What what are the member? I
don't remember.
Entering the stream
once returner
no returner
and then Arhat.
So these are called the four fruits
or the four results. Okay.
You enter the stream.
You come back to this world once.
You don't come back to this world and
you just go to a higher realm.
And then four you just
stop suffering existence. You don't have
suffering called Arhat enemy destroyer.
Okay.
Those are the four
fruits. They're called the four fruits.
Allah
of the four
those are the four fruits of the proper
relationship
to the four truths.
Four truths
four actions to take with the four
truths
and four results of those four actions.
Why is it mentioned here?
Yeah.
I'll let it go. I'll say it.
If there's no four truths
then you can't relate to those four
truths in the four classical ways. This
one is called Buddhism.
Four truths
the four actions are Buddhism. Okay.
And then if you do relate to the four
truths with the four proper ways you
reach
the four fruits. So now you got like 12.
Four four and four.
Who's talking?
The other guy is still going. Like,
yeah, go on. If there's no four truths,
you know, I don't see how you can have
four actions, and then you ain't going
to get to the four places you got to go
through. Got it?
He's still and the guy says like,
Mhm, good point. Good point. Okay, he's
listening.
All right, not like us.
And uh so, he's like
He's like letting the other guy go on,
which is a classical, classical method.
All right? This is a classical,
classical method.
Let the guy hang himself.
Oh, keep going. Keep going.
Okay. All right. Uh in debate, this is a
classical method. It's called Tal Gyer
Prasangika.
All right.
Next.
Um how are we doing on time? We By the
way, in 15 minutes we'll start Q&A.
Roughly.
Yeah.
Or we'll see how it goes.
I think it's a verse, you guys. Am I
right? Is it verse five?
Yeah.
Okay.
So, this is an interesting point, okay?
The other guy says,
"According to you, there's no Dharma."
Which means there's no four
truths.
Cuz that was the original Dharma. That
was the first Dharma ever spoken on this
planet.
Okay?
Lord Buddha sitting in the park
on the grass, and there's five guys
around him
who used to be
tiger cubs
four cubs and one mommy
and then he's saying
he's teaching them
after being silent for seven weeks cuz
he thought no one could understand.
Maybe he was right. I don't know.
But he's teaching for the first time.
The teaching was the four truths, okay?
If you practice that teaching well
you will reach the four fruits.
Okay? And and that's the real
Sangha.
Okay? It's not monks and nuns. Okay? The
the true Sangha
is people who have seen emptiness. Okay?
That that's the real community
of Buddhism. Okay? That's the real
Buddhist community is the people who
have seen emptiness. Only them.
They're the real Sangha. So
here's the the other guy still talking.
Okay? We're getting pretty deep into the
chapter and he's still letting the other
guy talk. He's being very patient.
Okay? Giving the guy rope to hang
himself.
Okay?
And he's saying, "Oh, really?" And the
guy says
"Look, I'll tell you something else."
And the guy is like, "All right.
I'll tell you something else."
"What?
According to you, there's no four truths
cuz they're all empty."
"Okay.
And if there's no four truths, no one
can practice them."
"Okay. And if no one can practice them,
no one reach the four fruits."
"Okay. And that means there's no
Sangha."
"Yeah, I I see your point. And that
means there's no Buddha."
Dharma
Sangha
Buddha. There's no
You know, you're like the ultimate
non-Buddhist, you know.
The definition of a Buddhist
is a person who takes refuge in the
three jewels,
which means emptiness.
Okay?
A person who's trying to understand
emptiness is a Buddhist.
And if you're not, you're not.
Okay? So, now the attack got heavy.
What's he say?
Oh,
if your ideas are true, Arya Nagarjuna,
if everything's empty, which means
nothing matters, I should sit and stare
at a wall.
Right? Then there's no
three jewels,
and there's no Buddhism.
Okay? His attack is getting worse and
worse.
Okay? Now he's accusing the greatest
Buddhist of all time after Buddha of not
being a Buddhist. Okay? Got it? And by
the way, Arya Nagarjuna went through
this stuff with people.
He he he had this, you know, and
normally when a new
thinker who's correct comes to a world,
they get hanged or crucified or,
you know, all kinds of stuff. All right?
Cuz people are like, "What?"
You know?
I'm happy with my
donuts and
Okay. Uh
Yeah, then there's no three jewels.
Okay? The attack is getting worse and
worse.
Somebody just said Nagarjuna doesn't
believe in the
three jewels,
which means he's not a Buddhist.
Okay.
Uh
I'll go one more
I'll do one more step and then then I'd
like to talk about
houses and then I'd take questions.
If there's time.
Okay.
Next picture.
Yeah.
Uh
No, huh?
Um
He says
Now the other guy's still going, okay?
And and you know, I'm sorry you're going
to have to leave the class with the
other guy.
Um
And I end the doctrine of if there's no
three jewels, okay? If there's no three
jewels
then there's no
morality.
Okay?
Somehow his attack
is worse than Buddhism.
Okay? It's worse than saying there's no
Buddhism.
He's going deeper.
He says if there's no three jewels
then there's no Buddhism. If there's no
Buddhism, there's no morality, okay?
And uh
And then you know, here's his logic,
okay?
If there's no three jewels
then there's no morality.
Meaning
it's not true that if you treat other
people well, good things will happen to
you. And it's not true that if you hurt
other people, bad things will happen to
you. The laws of
karma
are wrong.
If there's no three jewels, the laws of
karma are
don't exist in the world. And that would
be a true
glob- that would be a universe disaster.
You know, there would be no reason not
to kill somebody if you like their
t-shirt.
You know, seriously. You know,
if you see what I mean?
Then you couldn't sit in this room
together. You'd be like
You know,
wouldn't wear a nice shawl.
Someone might kill you.
And there'd be no law against it.
You know,
everyone would just kill other when they
want something, they would bomb the
other side.
Okay? This would be the
a- among true barbarians, among animals.
It would be if you want something or you
disagree with someone, bomb them. Try to
kill them. You know, then then that
would be the result
if there was no three jewels in the
world. If there was no three jewels,
the right thing, the smart thing to do
when you when another country bothers
you is to try to kill all of them. Okay?
That would be the best thing to do.
You see what I mean? Okay? If there's no
three jewels,
then people should just kill each other
when they want ice cream. You see, you
know what I mean? Why not?
Okay? Then why not?
Okay?
And then he says
So, we got two things so far. If there's
no three jewels,
there's no laws of
ethics, morality. There's no Nothing
happens to if you hurt somebody.
And you can get what you want if you can
bomb more cleverly than the other
people.
Okay? And then third one, then he goes
to another one.
The other guy, right? He says the world
could not speak to each other.
There would be no languages. There would
be no communication.
The world could not
communicate. The world could not
say things to each other. There would be
no language
in the world."
Okay. Now, I challenge you today
in your meditations, okay, in your
retreat.
What the heck? How does he get there?
How does he get there? Okay?
If the three jewels didn't exist. I told
the AI, "Give me three ladies covered
with jewels."
And that's the best he could do.
All right, I'm sorry.
Okay? If there was three things would
happen
if there's no three jewels in the world.
A, no three jewels.
B,
no karma and consequences. No morality,
no ethics
in any religion. And then number three,
no language, no expression, no way to
talk.
How does he make that leap?
Okay? How does the other guy make that
leap? By the way, I'm Let me check
something.
By the way, that's the end of the other
guy's rant. Okay? Rant means rant.
Okay? Like that's he's finally finished,
okay? But the way he finishes is
mysterious.
And you guys have to figure it out. And
I'll give $99 tomorrow.
Or no, this afternoon. When is No.
Half hour is too too short, right?
Yeah, tomorrow I'll give 100 bucks to
whoever gives the best answer. What's
the question again?
He says
By the way, if you're going to be
a really good student by tomorrow, give
me the whole flow.
Give me the whole flow. Look, Aryadeva
Nagarjuna. If everything is empty, then
there's no four
truths. If there's no four truths,
there's no four ways to
do the four truths. If there's no
ultimate way to do the four truths,
there's no four
results of doing the four truths. If
there's no four results of doing the
truths, there's no Buddha either, which
means there's no
three jewels. And if there's no three
jewels, then
What was it?
Yeah, there's no cause and effect. That
you can kill and then nothing happen to
you. And if that's true, then there's no
language.
Okay, especially towards the end it gets
a little mysterious.
Okay. And why does Why does Nagarjuna go
there?
Okay, why does Aryadeva Nagarjuna go
there? You got to talk about
it. Okay.
Uh
Okay, we'll continue in the next class
with that.
I'm at 6.7. I'm sure Tim will remind me.
Okay, I don't always finish as much as
I'm supposed to finish. Okay. We're
going to talk about the three houses.
And five houses, sorry.
I was just testing you. Um
Okay, you got those pictures, you guys?
Prince Princeton Prince Princeton. Yeah.
Okay, so uh
those of you who weren't here yesterday
or you were asleep
Um which normally happens towards the
end of the week. Um
So, with the
uh the MBA eMBA university, we went on a
field trip. We talked at Princeton, near
Princeton.
Uh
and uh we visited
Princeton, and we went to the We saw
some of the classical houses
uh at Princeton, and I was describing
how beautiful it is, this relationship
uh between the houses
and the university, okay? So, the
university is like this big
thing that pays for everything.
And they have How much did we say? $31
billion.
They're sitting on $31 billion.
ACI is sitting on $31.
Now, but you got to have a You have a
university, they keep the money, they
keep things running, they make sure
everybody's doing their thing
uh
the right way. And then there's
departments or houses, okay? And you
specialize. You don't try to get
10 PhDs at the same time. You
You You go into a So, we're going to
talk about this idea of ACI being houses
because
the original ACI foundation course is 18
courses, takes 7 years to do properly.
It has been done in one weekend.
By a certain naughty ex-monk.
Which is
Anyway,
and he copied He spent the whole weekend
He started on Friday afternoon, and he
copied the answer keys into the
homeworks, and turned them in, and he
finished by Monday morning.
And then I said
I said, "Go to some place."
And anyway,
it is possible.
But, it was designed to take six or
seven years, okay? And
then after that, there was a Diamond Way
course,
which was designed to take six or seven
years. So, now you got 14 years.
If you add Lam Rim,
Steps of the Path, then that's a We took
14 years.
And I did it
in my talkative way,
and I was not in a big rush. I think it
should be done
happily.
My teacher did it for 30 years, so I
saved you half the time.
Okay, so
that's And then, you know, you want to
tack on a three-year retreat.
So, how many years have you got? 31
years now.
And then, what's the fifth thing we do?
Um meditation. You know. Okay, anyway,
it's too much. You don't go to Princeton
and get a PhD in everything.
You get a PhD in one thing.
And there are requirements to go to
other classes. Like in my religion
department, I was required to take some
psychology and stuff like that.
Okay, so anyway,
what we're trying to do is allow you to
specialize and become a master
at one thing.
And then, of course, you should have
some background in other things.
But, what we need at ACI in the next
generation after grandpa,
we need masters. We need people who are
masters of meditation. And then, we need
people who are masters of retreat. And
then, we need people who are masters of
the classics. And then, we need people
who are masters of Lam Rim. And then, we
need people who are masters of the
Diamond Way. Because we need teachers
for the next generation. We need
And it can't be impossible to be a
teacher. It can't take 50 years to be a
teacher cuz then you only have one year
to teach and then you die.
So, you know, it's too much.
So, we're trying to create a way where
you could join a house, grow up in a
house,
and then become a master in the house.
And then when somebody even from another
house wants to learn to meditate, they
come to you.
And they come to Samadhi house and they
say, "You know, I'm a classics master or
I'm a
we treat master, mountain master.
But I would like to to to know some of
this other stuff. You know, can you can
you can your master teach some classes?"
So, that's the goal is to create
different masters. We got to talk about
how we do it, but the general idea is
there's a university
that takes basically they take care of
the business. stuff
They keep the rules and stuff like that.
And then there's five departments or
five houses. And they specialize and
they the university takes care of the
paperwork.
We got red tape bureaucracy.
How did that come in my mind? I don't
know.
Short circuit.
Somebody else takes care of the weird
stuff.
You know, and then you you depart you
have So, you got to have a Tim is up
here, okay? And his staff and then we
all have our separate houses. And there
should be a nice balance. You know,
if we run out of money, Tim should be
there.
If we have a program we really want to
do, he should disappear.
Right?
Okay. So, like that. I mean, somebody
has to keep the standards. Next picture.
Is it Is that the order I gave you? I
don't know.
Yeah, okay.
I'm going to review the five houses
quickly
just for people who didn't catch
yesterday's class cuz yesterday's class
was technically a translation class.
So, here we go.
You can join Classics House.
Basically, we'll talk about the
requirements each day, okay? But,
Classics House basically
preserves the classics, translates the
classics, and focuses on the classics.
This is the 18
foundation courses of ACE. This is the
baby Geshe course.
And, we'll talk more about it, okay? I I
personally
And, what I'm what I'm encouraging you
this week
is think about these five pictures. I
find pictures are easier than blah blah.
Just remember the five pictures. Here's
a, you know, wise-looking guy with a
book.
And, is that what you want to be? Is
that what If if I said, "You can be a
master.
You you can learn to be a master. Do you
want to be this guy?
Does that make you like, "Wow, that's
really cool."?
Okay? Or, are you like, "Oh, too many
facts, you know."
Okay. Next house.
Next picture.
Uh see.
Uh it's a Samadhi house.
No, there you go. Uh
do you want to be a meditation master?
Okay?
And, do you want to help people
to learn to meditate? Is that Is that
what you would like to do in your life?
Would you like to be a basically
meditation teacher?
Would you like to
focus
on the meditation arts
and and get good at it? And, by the way,
uh
we got the stuff, okay? If If you're
serious about meditation, you cannot
learn it anywhere as well as you can
learn it in ACI. Not possible.
They don't even have the books. They
have no idea.
They have no tradition. They just make
up something.
You know, you go to some yoga studio.
They're like, "Close your eyes. Think of
You know, notice the donut in your
stomach."
You know, and and we have
great great great tradition, real
tradition.
And And we've translated most of the
books and
and we have a living tradition. Somebody
asked me, "How many meditations you
doing for
Tim?" I said, "101."
"Oh, do you know that many?" No, I had
to cut it.
Okay? I mean, you meditate in the
monastery for 25 years every morning for
2 hours or something. Then
you don't do the same one over and over
again, okay? Right?
There's many many beautiful ones.
And that's a master.
That's a master.
Okay, third one.
Now, I call it mountain house.
And that's a retreat master.
Would you like to be a retreat master?
Is it attractive to you
to come out to Diamond Mountain and go
into a
go into a cabin and do retreat?
Is that what calls to you? And is that
what you would like to be a master of,
okay?
Uh one thing I wanted to say is what I
talked with Stanley. Stanley has a new
organization called Innovation Retreats.
They are mostly focusing on retreats for
business people or artists or or writers
or musicians or
I'd say mainly business people.
I can imagine a retreat
master
who has a dual specialty, double
specialty.
And so, somebody comes to them and says,
"I want to do a retreat."
And then they say,
"Do you want a Buddhist retreat, or do
you want an innovation retreat, or
something like that?" You know, they'll
say,
"What do you want to use the retreat
for?
Do you want to get enlightened, or do
you want to build a quarter
billion-dollar business? What's What
Would you like to make new products
at your business, you know? Would you
like to learn how to be creative?"
So, I I imagine there will be both
specialties, okay?
Two different kinds of
retreat.
Next one.
I call it staircase house.
And
it's really a synthesized
Buddhism.
Okay? It's a deep
La- Islam. Okay? And it took 14 years
for me to teach Islam.
It took 7 years to teach ACI.
So, it's supposed to be the short path.
But it's deep. It's totally deep. Don't
Don't blow it off. Don't think it's not
important. In a way, it's more
experiential
than the classics.
You can get through the classics and
still be an
But you can't get through the Lamrim and
still be I shouldn't use that language.
My boss is here.
But you see what I mean?
Okay? Lamrim changes your heart
drastically.
And maybe that's where you want to go.
Okay?
Maybe you want to be a master of Lamrim.
And by the way,
the audiences for Lamrim are bigger,
meaning more people
will listen to Lamrim than will listen
to the Geshe class. And okay.
I told Veronica, we started my Geshe
class with 60 people. At the end we had
two.
Then you can't find people who are crazy
to do that.
My teacher taught Lama for 30 years.
More and more people came. That's me.
Okay, number five.
Diamond House. It's not so much focused
on diamond as emptiness.
It's more focused on diamond in the
sense of
Somebody told me yesterday, you should
call it hidden Buddhism.
And I kind of like it.
You know, I kind of like it. And And the
idea is that you work in a company for
19 years in Manhattan.
And you do all the things that
you do all the things that an executive
does
for 19 years and no one knows you're a
Buddhist.
And you change the You change a thousand
people
in the building.
And because of that that becomes
the most successful manufacturing
business in the history of New York
City.
Okay?
Because it's all Buddhist who don't know
they're Buddhist.
Got it?
Okay? And that's That's the real secret
way.
That's the real secret way.
And that's sexy. That's really fun.
Okay? So you choose what kind of master
you want to be. If you want to learn to
ring your bell at the right time
that's part of Diamond Way.
But it is obviously not the main thing.
I can
It's part of the Diamond Way course
that you will ring your bell at the
right
That's it.
That's what you're learning at the
Temple College.
I think it's not enough. I think it's
not the full thing.
I think you have to do
secret Buddhism. But, that's
So, anyway, you're going to learn both,
okay?
All right.
Next picture.
What is the next picture? Oh, yeah.
Uh
It's a joke for those people in the MBA
program.
Uh no one has ever asked me
to prove I went to Princeton.
And when I got my job in the diamond
business, I offered to show them my
degree, and they said, "We don't care,
and we're paying you $7 an hour."
And I'm like, "Wait a minute. I got this
piece of paper." And they're like, "Take
That's the truth, okay?
Why I put this up here, uh when we went
to Princeton,
uh we were debating what language is on
the degree.
And it's Latin, okay?
But, the point is
at the at that class,
I said, "Cum laude." in the middle,
which means uh
the best of the best.
Uh
it means you got a super degree.
And and at the time, someone asked me,
"Well, how many students get that?"
And I said, "One out of 100."
Then I checked online cuz I want to make
sure I'm not lying
to all my students. And uh
there was a scandal recently at
Princeton
uh because
the laude, the honors,
is decided not by the university, by the
house.
The house decides honors.
The university does not decide the
honors, okay? Whether you get a super
degree
comes from your immediate professors.
And it does not come from the
university. It doesn't come from TIP.
It comes from the director of your house
or the assistant director of your house,
okay? laude. And it got to 41%.
And then the university said, "Stop.
You know, this is corruption, you know?"
And and people would go to their
professor and say, "You're so handsome
or you're so beautiful, and can I take
you to dinner?"
And then they'd say, "Oh, you're
honors laude, you know?" And it
became a kind of corruption within this
university because they're because the
the the university as a whole, ACI as a
whole, wasn't watching the houses.
And the house went crazy. And the house
said, "Everybody's good person.
Everybody gets honors, you know?" Then I
was really embarrassed. I told them I'm
one out of 100. I'm 41 out of 100,
you know, which is almost half.
Uh
then they had a big um scandal and and
the university put a number on it. I
think it's now it's 10% honors.
Something like that. The university
stepped in
and said, "You're you're not keeping
standards. You're not running a good
house."
So, I I think there should The reason I
put the degree up here
is uh
you think about this structure. I think
you need both.
Uh sometimes the house gets out of
control and the university has to say,
"Come on.
You know, and sometimes the university's
too slow and boring and the house has to
say, "We're We're doing something cool.
We don't care."
You know, I think there has to be this
tension
between Tim and the rest of us.
You know, and uh so I look forward to
that. With With the house structure,
we bring in more creativity, more
excitement, but we also bring in the
possibility of chaos.
So there has to be an overall,
you know, structure and
especially from finances, uh you know,
from money cuz
in the end if the department needs
money, they go to the university.
And uh who pays the department
professors is
the university.
So the university maintains some
order
and and some standards for the
university and the house doesn't go
crazy and do whatever they want.
But then again, the house can do
creative things because the university
is boring.
Okay? Got it?
All right. Uh which means next picture.
And I will stop in the next 5 minutes,
don't worry.
Uh we propose to have a director and an
assistant director of each house. Okay?
Which means we need how many?
10. 5 * 2.
Okay. We need 10 good people.
Okay? So and and we're thinking
that
uh between now and Kyoto, which is
December, we cook this project. We cook
the five houses idea. That gives us 2
months or something like that.
And we cook all the ideas and then maybe
you come to Tim
and you say, "By the way, I have an idea
for a director of Samadhi house." And
Tim says, "Who?" And you say, "Uh me."
Okay? And God bless. Okay, do it. If you
want to be If you want to lose your
hair, I mean if you want to
run
a house or you'd like You think it'd be
fun to be a director in the house or or
help run a house. And by the way, in my
idea, you can still do your other
projects. I don't care.
You know, I I almost respect people. I
guess that I want to do a separate, you
know, yoga master thing. I I don't care.
That's your thing.
You want to do Just don't get in
trouble. Don't do anything illegal,
which means sex and taxes.
Okay? Those two things you're not
allowed to do.
But, you know, you want to do other
stuff as long as you're not hurting
anybody, I don't care. But But, under
the
five houses structure,
you can you can be a director, you can
be an assistant director. Okay?
And I think it should be international
and I don't think it should all be
Americans. There's no Americans who
even do ACI very well, except a few.
So, uh
you know, it's up to up to you guys.
Uh I got one more picture, I
think.
Oh, here's the bad news. Just when you
were excited.
Oh, there's the director and the
assistant director. You figure out which
is which. Next.
Oh, yeah, this one. Um
You You got out of the 18 courses, but
you still have to take five.
That's the bottom line. If you're from
If you're a nice, intelligent young lady
from Malaysia,
this is what I'm saying.
You You still got to take the five
courses, okay?
Otherwise, it's going to end up like
this lady who's asking the French guy in
Paris how to get to the third subway
stop. He speaks French. She speaks
American
English, okay? And they have a
communication breakdown on the street.
Understand?
I mean,
to some extent, we all have to speak the
ACI language, okay? If you don't know
the basics of Buddhism,
I don't want you to be in a house, okay?
To get into a house,
which is called member status, okay? To
get into a house,
you first you have to finish five
courses, okay? I took away 13 courses.
You should kiss my feet. Okay?
Uh
All right. Minimum five courses, all
right?
And
Okay? And that's to get into any house.
You cannot get into any house
as a member, okay? The lowest level is
member, which is already a high level.
You already can speak ACI-nese.
ACI-lish?
Anyway, okay? You got to speak the ACI
language. Otherwise, we can't
communicate, okay?
You got to do these five courses.
And we estimate, me and Tim,
we estimate that's about 18 months of
work. So, if you can't do if you're not
willing to do 18 months of work to get
into a house,
then
you'll go somewhere else, okay?
Uh most of you have already finished
most of these courses, I think. And
we're not asking you to do them again.
We're just saying, in your life, you
should finish these five.
Or or you can't speak
Buddhism.
You don't really know Buddhism, okay?
All right. I'm sorry I ran over, which
is very unusual. And I'm sorry I didn't
get in the Q&A, which is extremely
unusual, right, shopping? And
we'll do it Q&A in the next class. So
take a 15-minute break, pee pee break
and drink, okay? You're in
Arizona, you're in the desert. You got
to drink. When you drink, there's a
cause and effect.
Okay? All right, bye.